Hi there. I'm Hasan. I'm an artist.
مرحباً، أنا حسن وأنا فنان
And usually when I tell people I'm an artist,
وفي العادة عندما أخبر الناس بأنني فنان
they just look at me and say, "Do you paint?"
فإنهم ينظرون إلي ويسألون: "هل ترسم؟"
or "What kind of medium do you work in?"
أو "ما هي طبيعة عملك؟"
Well most of my work that I work with
حسناً، معظم عملي الذي أقوم به
is really a little bit about methodologies of working
يدور بعض الشيء حول منهجيات العمل
rather than actually a specific discipline
بدلاً من ارتباطه بمجال معين
or a specific technique.
أو تقنية محددة
So what I'm really interested in is creative problem solving.
وبالتالي، اهتمامي الحقيقي يتمركز حول حل المشكلات بطريقة إبداعية
And I had a little bit of a problem a few years ago.
فقبل عدة سنوات، واجهتني مشكلة صغيرة نوعاً ما
So let me show you a little of that.
دعوني أريكم بعض من ذلك
So it started over here.
بدأت المشكلة هنا
And this is the Detroit airport in June 19th of 2002.
وهذا هو مطار ديترويت في تاريخ 19 يونيو، 2002
I was flying back to the U.S. from an exhibition overseas.
كنت عائداً إلى الولايات المتحدة من معرض أقيم في الخارج
And as I was coming back,
وفي أثناء عودتي
well I was taken by the FBI, met by an FBI agent,
حسناً، تم ضبطي من قبل مكتب التحقيق الفدرالي حيث قابلني أحد عملائهم
and went into a little room
وأخذت إلى غرفة صغيرة
and he asked me all sorts of questions --
وسألني العميل الفيدرالي جميع أنواع الأسئلة
"Where were you? What were you doing? Who were you talking with?
"أين كنت؟ ماذا كنت تفعل؟ من كنت تحادث؟
Why were you there? Who pays for your trips?" --
لماذا كنت هناك؟ من يدفع تكاليف رحلاتك؟"
all these little details.
كل هذه التفاصيل الصغيرة
And then literally just out of nowhere,
وفجأة بدون أي مقدمات
the guy asks me, "Where were you September 12th?"
سألني الرجل "أين كنت في تاريخ 12 من سبتمبر؟"
And when most of us get asked, "Where were you September 12th?"
وحينما يسأل أغلبنا "أين كنت في تاريخ 12 من سبتمبر؟"
or any date for that fact,
أو أي تاريخ آخر
it's like, "I don't exactly remember, but I can look it up for you."
فإن الرد يكون كهذا "لا أتذكر بالضبط ولكن يمكنني البحث لك عن ذلك"
So I pulled out my little PDA,
وقمت بإخراج مساعدي الشخصي الرقمي
and I said, "Okay, let's look up my appointments for September 12th."
وقلت: "حسناً، لننظر إلى مواعيدي في تاريخ 12 من سبتمبر"
I had September 12th -- from 10:00 a.m. to 10:30 a.m., I paid my storage bill.
في 12 سبتمبر من الساعة 10:00 حتى الساعة 10:30 صباحاً، دفعت فاتورة مستودعي
From 10:30 a.m. to 12:00 p.m., I met with Judith who was one of my graduate students at the time.
ومن 10:30 صباحاً حتى 12:00 مساءاً قابلت جوديث وهي إحدى طالبات الدراسات العليا لدي في ذلك الوقت
From 12:00 p.m. to 3:00 p.m., I taught my intro class,
ومن 12:00 حتى 3:00 مساءاً قمت بتعليم صفي للمبتدئين
3:00 p.m. to 6:00 p.m., I taught my advanced class.
3:00 مساءاً وحتى 6:00 مساءاً قمت بتدريس صف المتقدمين
"Where were you the 11th?" "Where were you the 10th?"
"أين كنت في الـ 11؟" "أين كنت في الـ10؟"
"Where were you the 29th? the 30th?"
"أين كنت في الـ 29؟ الـ 30؟"
"Where were you October 5th?"
"أين كنت في 5 أكتوبر؟"
We read about six months of my calendar.
قرأنا ما يقارب الستة أشهر من تقويمي
And I don't think he was expecting me to have such detailed records
ولا أظن أنه توقع أن يكون لدي سجلات مفصلة بهذه الدرجة
of what I did.
لجدول أعمالي
But good thing I did,
ولكن كان من حسن حظي أنها لدي
because I don't look good in orange.
لأن اللون البرتقالي لا يناسبني
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So he asked me --
وسألني
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
"So this storage unit that you paid the rent on,
"هذا المخزن الذي دفعت إيجاره،
what did you have in it?"
ماذا يوجد بداخله؟"
This was in Tampa, Florida,
كان هذا في تامبا في فلوريدا
so I was like, "Winter clothes that I have no use for in Florida.
فقلت: "ملابس شتوية لا أحتاجها في فلوريدا
Furniture that I can't fit in my ratty apartment.
وأثاث لا تكفيه شقتي المهترئة
Just assorted garage sale junk,
مجرد خردة متنوعة تصلح لمزاد في المرآب،
because I'm a pack rat."
وذلك لأنني هاو لجمع الخردة"
And he looks at me really confused and says, "No explosives?"
ونظر إليّ نظرة حائرة وقال: "لا يوجد متفجرات؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I was like, "No, no. I'm pretty certain there were no explosives.
فقلت: "لا، لا. أنا متأكد جداً بأنه لا يوجد متفجرات
And if there were, I would have remembered that one."
ولو كان هناك متفجرات لكنت تذكرت ذلك"
And he's still a little confused,
ومازال حائراً بعض الشيء
but I think that anyone who talks to me for more than a couple of minutes
ولكني أعتقد بأنه من يتحدث معي أكثر من بضع دقائق
realizes I'm not exactly a terrorist threat.
يدرك بأنني لا أشكل خطراً ارهابياً
And so we're sitting there,
وكنا جالسين هناك
and eventually after about an hour, hour and a half of just going back and forth,
وفي النهاية بعد حوالي الساعة أو الساعة والنصف من الصول والجول في الحديث،
he says, "Okay, I have enough information here.
قال: "حسناً، لدي معلومات كافية هنا
I'm going to pass this onto the Tampa office. They're the ones who initiated this.
سأحول هذه إلى مكتب التامبا. هم الذين بدأوا هذا.
They'll follow up with you, and we'll take care of it."
سيتابعون معك وسنهتم بالأمر"
I was like, "Great."
فأجبته: "رائع"
So I got home and the phone rings,
عدت إلى المنزل ودق جرس الهاتف
and a man introduced himself.
وقام الرجل بالتعريف بنفسه
Basically this is the FBI offices in Tampa
وأساساً، هذا هو فرع مكتب التحقيق الفيدرالي في تامبا
where I spent six months of my life --
حيث قضيت ستة أشهر من حياتي
back and forth, not six months continuously.
ذهاباً وإياباً وليست ستة أشهر متواصلة
By the way, you folks know that in the United States,
وعلى فكرة، كما تعلمون أنه في الولايات المتحدة
you can't take photographs of federal buildings,
لا يمكنك تصوير المباني الفدرالية
but Google can do it for you.
ولكن جوجل يمكنه فعل ذلك من أجلك
So to the folks from Google, thank you.
للزملاء في جوجل، شكراً جزيلاً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So I spent a lot of time in this building.
قضيت الكثير من الوقت في هذا المبنى
Questions like:
أسئلة كـ:
"Have you ever witnessed or participated in any act
"هل سبق وأن شاهدت أو شاركت في أي حدث
that may be detrimental to the United States or a foreign nation?"
قد يضر الولايات المتحدة أو دولة أخرى؟"
And you also have to consider the state of mind you're in
وأيضاً يتوجب عليك أن تضع في الحسبان حالتك العقلية التي تكون فيها
when you're doing this.
وانت تفعل ذلك
You're basically face-to-face with someone
فأنت تجلس وجهاً لوجه مع شخص
that essentially decides life or death.
يتحكم بشكل أساسي بحياتك ومماتك
Or questions such as -- actually, during the polygraph,
أو أسئلة من قبيل -- في الواقع، خلال جهاز كشف الكذب،
which was how it finally ended after nine consecutive of them --
والتي انتهت أخيراً بعد تسعة اختبارات متوالية بجهاز كشف الكذب،
one of the polygraph questions was ...
وكان أحد الأسئلة التي طرحت علي خلال جهاز كشف الكذب...
well the first one was, "Is your name Hasan?" "Yes."
حسناً الأول كان: "هل اسمك حسن؟" "نعم"
"Are we in Florida?" "Yes." "Is today Tuesday?" "Yes."
"هل نحن في فلوريدا؟" "نعم". "هل اليوم الثلاثاء؟" "نعم"
Because you have to base it on a yes or no.
لأنه يجب عليك الإجابة بنعم أو لا
Then, of course, the next question is:
وبالطبع السؤال التالي سيكون:
"Do you belong to any groups that wish to harm the United States?"
"هل تنتمي لأي مجموعات تريد إيذاء الولايات المتحدة؟"
I work at a university.
أنا أعمل في جامعة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I was like, "Maybe you want to ask some of my colleagues that directly."
فقلت: "ربما تريد سؤال هذا لأحد زملائي في العمل بشكل مباشر".
But they said, "Okay, aside from what we had discussed,
ولكنهم قالوا: "حسناً، بعيداً عما قمنا بمناقشته،
do you belong to any groups that wish to harm the United States?"
هل تنتمي لأي مجموعات تريد إيذاء الولايات المتحدة؟"
I was like, "No."
فقلت: "لا"
So at the end of six months of this
وبذلك بنهاية ستة أشهر من هذا
and nine consecutive polygraphs,
وتسعة اختبارات متوالية بجهاز كشف الكذب،
they said, "Hey, everything's fine."
قالوا: "كل شيء على مايرام"
I was like, "I know. That's what I've been trying to tell you guys all along.
فقلت: "أنا أعلم، وذلك ما كنت أحاول إخباركم به طوال الوقت.
I know everything's fine."
أعلم أن كل شيء على مايرام"
So they're looking at me really odd.
وكانوا ينظرون إليّ بنظرات غريبة جداً
And it's like, "Guys, I travel a lot."
وقلت: "أنا أسافر كثيراً".
This is with the FBI.
هذه المحادثة مع مكتب التحقيق الفيدرالي.
And I was like, "All we need is Alaska not to get the last memo,
قلت: "كل ما نحتاجه أن لا تكون ألاسكا آخر من يعلم بالأمر
and here we go all over again."
لكي لا نعيد الكرة من جديد"
And there was a sincere concern there.
وكان هنالك قلق حقيقي بشأن هذا الأمر.
And he was like, "You know, if you get into trouble,
فقال:"أتعلم، إن وقعت في ورطة"
give us a call -- we'll take care of it."
اتصل بنا -- سنتولى نحن بالأمر".
So ever since then, before I would go anywhere, I would call the FBI.
ومنذ ذلك الحين، وقبل سفري لأي مكان، أقوم بالاتصال بمكتب التحقيق الفيدرالي.
I would tell them, "Hey guys, this is where I'm going. This is my flight.
كنت اخبرهم، "مرحباً، هذه هي وجهتي، وهذه هي رحلتي
Northwest flight seven coming into Seattle
الرحلة السابعة لنورث ويست والقادمة من سياتل
on March 12th" or whatever.
في 12 من مارس" أو أياً كان.
A couple weeks later, I'd call again, let them know.
وبعد عدة أسابيع، اتصل بهم مرة أخرى، وأعلمهم بوجهتي.
It wasn't that I had to, but I chose to.
ولم يكن علي القيام بذلك، ولكني اخترت القيام بهذا.
Just wanted to say, "Hey guys.
أردت فقط اخباركم، "مرحباً.
Don't want to make it look like I'm making any sudden moves."
لا أريد جعل الأمر يبدو وكأنني اتخذ أي خطوات مفاجئة".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I don't want you guys to think that I'm about to flee.
"لا اريد ان تعتقدوا انني على وشك الفرار.
Just letting you know. Heads up."
أردت فقط اخباركم. إشعار".
And so I just kept doing this over and over and over.
وهكذا بقيت أقوم بذلك مراراً، مراراً، وتكراراً.
And then the phone calls turned into emails,
والاتصال الهاتفي تحول لرسائل البريد الالكتروني،
and the emails got longer and longer and longer ...
وأصبحت رسائل البريد الالكتروني أطول، وأطول، وأطول ...
with pictures,
مع صور،
with travel tips.
ومع نصائح للسفر.
Then I'd make websites.
وبعدها، قمت بإنشاء مواقع.
And then I built this over here. Let me go back to it over here.
وبعدها، قمت بإنشاء هذا هنا، اسمحوا لي أن أعود إليه هنا.
So I actually designed this back in 2003.
وفي الحقيقة صممت هذا الموقع سابقاً في 2003.
So this kind of tracks me at any given moment.
وهذا الموقع يتقفى أثري في أي لحظة.
I wrote some code for my mobile phone.
وكتبت رمزاً لهاتفي النقال.
Basically, what I decided is okay guys, you want to watch me, that's cool.
بشكل أساسي، ما قررته أنه حسناً تريدون مراقبتي، سأقبل بذلك.
But I'll watch myself. It's okay.
ولكن سأقوم مراقبة نفسي بنفسي، لا بأس.
You don't have to waste your energy or your resources.
ليس عليكم هدر طاقتكم أو مواردكم.
And I'll help you out.
وسأساعدكم.
So in the process, I start thinking, well what else might they know about me?
وأثناء ذلك، بدأت بالتفكير، ماذا الذي أيضاً يعرفونه عني؟
Well they probably have all my flight records,
لديهم على الارجح كافة سجلات رحلاتي
so I decided to put all my flight records from birth online.
فقررت وضع جميع سجلات رحلاتي منذ الولادة على الموقع.
So you can see, Delta 1252
فتستطيعون رؤية رحلة دلتا 1252
going from Kansas City to Atlanta.
المتوجهة من كنساس إلى أتلانتا.
And then you see, these are some of the meals that I've been fed on the planes.
وبعدها ترون بعضاً من الوجبات التي تناولتها على الطائرات.
This was on Delta 719
كان هذا في رحلة دلتا 719
going from JFK to San Francisco.
المتوجهة من جون إف كينيدي إلى سان فرانسيسكو.
See that? They won't let me on a plane with that,
أترون هذا؟ لن يسمحوا لي بركوب الطائرة مع هذا الشيء،
but they'll give it to me on the plane.
ولكن، سيعطونني إياه على متن الطائرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These are the airports that I hang out in,
هذه هي المطارات التي أتجول بها،
because I like airports.
لأنني أحب المطارات.
That's Kennedy airport, May 19th, Tuesday.
هذا هو مطار كينيدي، 19 مايو، الثلاثاء.
This is in Warsaw.
هذا في وارسو.
Singapore. You can see, they're kind of empty.
سنغافورة. ويمكنكم رؤية أنها نوعاً ما فارغة.
These images are shot really anonymously
هذه الصور التقطت بشكل عشوائي
to the point where it could be anyone.
لدرجة أنها قد تكون صورت من قبل أي شخص.
But if you can cross-reference this with the other data,
ولكن إن استطعت ربطها مع البيانات الأخرى،
then you're basically replaying the roll of the FBI agent
فعندها مبدئياً تعيد لعب دور عميل مكتب التحقيق الفيدرالي.
and putting it all together.
وبوضع كل ذلك معاً.
And when you're in a situation
وعندما تكون في موقف
where you have to justify every moment of your existence,
يتوجب عليك فيه تبرير كل لحظة من وجودك،
you're put in the situation where you react in a very different manner.
فتوضع في موقف حيث يتوجب عليك التصرف بسلوك مختلف جداً.
At the time that this was going on,
في ذلك الوقت، هذا كان ما يحدث ،
the last thing on my mind was "art project."
آخر ما خطر في ذهني "المشروع الفني".
I was certainly not thinking, hey, I got new work here.
أنا بالتأكيد لم أكن أفكر، مهلاً، حصلت على عمل جديد هنا.
But after going through this, after realizing, well what just happened?
ولكن بعد مروري بهذه التجربة وبعد ادراكي لما حدث للتو؟
And after piecing together this, this and this,
وبعد جمع هذا وهذا مع ذاك.
this way of actually trying to figure out what happened for myself
هذه الطريقة لمحاولة معرفة ما حدث لي.
eventually evolved into this,
تطورت في نهاية المطاف إلى هذا،
and it actually became this project.
وأصبح بالفعل هذا المشروع.
So these are the stores that I shop in -- some of them --
فهذه هي المتاجر التي اتبضع منها -- البعض منها --
because they need to know.
لأنهم بحاجة إلى معرفة هذا الأمر.
This is me buying some duck flavored paste
هذا أنا، وأقوم بشراء معجون بنكهة البط
at the Ranch 99 in Daly City
في مزرعة 99 في مدينة دالي
on Sunday, November 15th.
يوم الأحد، 15 نوفمبر
At Coreana Supermarket
في سوبرماركت كوريانا
buying my kimchi because I like kimchi.
اشتري الكيمتشي خاصتي لأنني أحبه.
And I bought some crabs too right around there,
واشتريت بعض السرطانات أيضا من هناك ،
and some chitlins at the Safeway in Emoryville.
وبعضاً من الشيتلين من سيفواي في إيموريفل
And laundry too. Laundry detergent at West Oakland --
والغسيل أيضاً. منظفات الغسيل من ويست اوكلاند --
East Oakland, sorry.
عذراً، إيست أوكلاند.
And then my pickled jellyfish
وبعدها القناديل المخللة.
at the Hong Kong Supermarket on Route 18 in East Brunswick.
في هونغ كونغ سوبر ماركت على شارع 18 في منطقة إيست برونزويك.
Now if you go to my bank records,
والآن، إذا توجهت لسجلاتي المصرفية.
it'll actually show something from there,
سيظهر لك شيئاً من هناك،
so you know that, on May 9th,
فأنتم ستعلمون أنه في 9 من مايو،
that I bought $14.79 in fuel from Safeway Vallejo.
قمت بشراء وقود بقيمة 14.79 $ من سيفواي فاليو.
So not only that I'm giving this information here and there,
فلم أكتفي فقط بإعطاء هذه المعلومات هنا وهناك ،
but now there's a third party,
ولكن الآن هناك طرف ثالث،
an independent third party, my bank,
طرف ثالث مستقل، مصرفي،
that's verifying that, yes indeed, I was there at this time.
والذي يؤكد، أنه نعم في الواقع ، كنت هناك في هذا الوقت.
So there's points, and these points are actually being cross-referenced.
فهناك نقاط، وهذه النقاط مرتبطة مع بعضها البعض,
And there's a verification taking place.
وهناك توكيد مجرى.
Sometimes they're really small purchases.
في بعض الأحيان، تكون بالفعل مشتريات قليلة.
So 34 cents foreign transaction fee.
34 سنت كرسوم للمعاملات الخارجية.
All of these are extracted directly from my bank accounts,
يتم سحب جميع هذه المصاريف مباشرة من حساباتي المصرفية،
and everything pops up right away.
ويظهر كل شيء على الفور.
Sometimes there's a lot of information.
أحيانا، هناك الكثير من المعلومات.
This is exactly where my old apartment in San Francisco was.
هنا بالضبط تقع شقتي القديمة في سان فرانسيسكو.
And then sometimes you get this.
ثم في بعض الأحيان تحصل على هذا.
Sometimes you just get this, just an empty hallway in Salt Lake City,
أحيانا تحصل فقط على هذا، مجرد رواق فارغ في سولت لايك سيتي ،
January 22nd.
22 من يناير
And I can tell you exactly who I was with, where I was,
واستطيع ان اقول لكم بالضبط كنت برفقة من وبمكان تواجدي،
because this is what I had to do with the FBI.
لأن ذلك ما كان علي القيام به مع مكتب التحقيق الفدرالي.
I had to tell them every little detail of everything.
كان يجب علي إخبارهم عن كل تفصيل صغير لكل شي.
I spend a lot of time on the road.
أقضي الكثير من الوقت على الطريق.
This is a parking lot in Elko, Nevada
هذا هو موقف للسيارات في إلكو، نيفادا
off of Route 80
طريق 80
at 8:01 p.m. on August 19th.
في الساعة 8:01 في 19 من أغسطس
I spend a lot of time in gas stations too -- empty train stations.
وكذلك، أقضي الكثير من الوقت في محطات الوقود -- محطات القطار فارغة.
So there's multiple databases.
لذا فإن هناك قواعد بيانات متعددة.
And there's thousands and thousands and thousands of images.
وهناك آلاف وآلاف وآلاف من الصور.
There's actually 46,000 images right now on my site,
في الواقع توجد حالياً 46000 صورة على موقعي،
and the FBI has seen all of them --
ورآهم جميعاً مكتب التحقيق الفدرالي --
at least I trust they've seen all of them.
على الأقل أنا واثق بأنهم قد رأوا جميع الصور.
And then sometimes you don't get much information at all,
وفي بعض الأحيان قد لا تحصل على أي معلومات على الإطلاق،
you just get this empty bed.
ستحصل فقط على سرير فارغ.
And sometimes you get a lot of text information and no visual information.
وأحياناً تحصل على كثير من المعلومات النصية وليس هناك معلومات مرئية.
So you get something like this.
فتحصل على شيء كهذا.
This, by the way, is the location of my favorite sandwich shop in California --
هذا، بالمناسبة، هو موقع متجر الشطائر المفضل لدي في كاليفورنيا --
Vietnamese sandwich.
شطيرة فيتنامية.
So there's different categorizations
ولذلك يوجد تصنيفات مختلفة
of meals eaten outside
لوجبات أكلتها في الخارج
empty train stations, empty gas stations.
محطات قطار فارغة، ومحطات وقود فارغة.
These are some of the meals that I've been cooking at home.
هذه هي بعض وجبات الطعام التي كنت أقوم بطهيها في المنزل
So how do you know these are meals eaten at home?
وكيف يمكنك أن تعرف أن هذه الوجبات أكلت في المنزل؟
Well the same plate shows up a whole bunch of times.
بظهور الطبق ذاته في جميع الأوقات.
So again, you have to do some detective work here.
ومرة أخرى، عليك القيام ببعض التحري هنا.
So sometimes the databases get so specific.
ففي بعض الأحيان البيانات تصبح محددة للغاية.
These are all tacos eaten in Mexico City
أكلت كل هذه التاكوز في مدينة مكسيكو
near a train station
بالقرب من محطة قطار
on July fifth to July sixth.
من 5 إلى 6 من يوليو.
At 11:39 a.m. was this one.
هذه كانت في الساعة 11:39 صباحاً
At 1:56 p.m. was this one. At 4:59 p.m. was this one.
وهذه في الساعة 1:56 مساءاً وهذه في الساعة 4:59 مساءاً
So I time-stamp my life every few moments.
فأوثق حياتي زمنياً كل لحظات قليلة.
Every few moments I shoot the image.
وكل بضع دقائق ألتقط صورة.
Now it's all done on my iPhone,
والآن كل شيء جهز على الـ آي فون خاصتي،
and it all goes straight up to my server,
ويصل كل شيء مباشرة لسيرفر خاصتي،
and my server does all the backend work
والسيرفر خاصتي يؤدي كافة العمل
and categorizes things and puts everything together.
ويصنف الأشياء ويضع كل شيء معاً.
They need to know where I'm doing my business,
وهم بحاجة الى معرفة مكان قضاء حاجتي،
because they want to know about my business.
لأنهم يريدون معرفة ذلك.
So on December 4th, I went here.
ففي الـ 4 من ديسمبر، أتيت إلى هنا.
And on Sunday, June 14th at 2009 --
وفي يوم الأحد، 14 من يونيو 2009 --
this was actually about two o'clock in the afternoon
كان هذا في 2 بعد الظهر
in Skowhegan, Maine -- this was my apartment there.
في كوهيجن، ماين -- كان شقتي تقع هناك.
So what you're basically seeing here
فما ترونه أساساً هنا
is all bits and pieces and all this information.
أجزاء ,مقاطع وجميع هذه المعلومات.
If you go to my site, there's tons of things.
وإذا زرتم موقعي، ستجدون العديد من الأشياء.
And really, it's not the most user-friendly interface.
وبالفعل، إنها ليست أكثر واجهات المستخدم ملائمة.
It's actually quite user-unfriendly.
وفي الحقيقة إنها ليست كذلك.
And one of the reasons, also being part of the user-unfriendliness,
ومن أحد الأسباب، وكونه جزءاً غير ملائم للمستخدم،
is that everything is there,
أن كل شيء يوجد هناك،
but you have to really work through it.
ولكن عليك العمل بجد
So by me putting all this information out there,
فبإخراجي لكل المعلومات هناك،
what I'm basically telling you is I'm telling you everything.
أخبركم أساساً بكل شيء.
But in this barrage of noise
ولكن في وابل الفيض من المعلومات
that I'm putting out,
التي أنشرها للخارج
I actually live an incredibly anonymous and private life.
أنا أعيش في الواقع حياة عادية وخاصة.
And you know very little about me actually.
وتعلمون عني القليل جداً في الواقع.
And really so I've come to the conclusion
وبالحقيقة توصلت لاستنتاج
that the way you protect your privacy,
أن طريقة حماية خصوصيتك،
particularly in an era where everything is cataloged
وبالتحديد في زمن يعرض فيه كل شيء
and everything is archived and everything is recorded,
وكل شيء يتم أرشفته وتسجيله
there's no need to delete information anymore.
فليس هناك داعٍ لمحو معلومات بعد الآن.
So what do you do when everything is out there?
ماذا تفعل إذا كان كل شيء يكشف للخارج؟
Well you have to take control over it.
عليك التحكم بذلك.
And if I give you this information directly,
وإذا قدمت لكم هذه المعلومات بشكل مباشر،
it's a very different type of identity
فإنها هويتي ستختلف كل الاختلاف
than if you were to try to go through and try to get bits and pieces.
عن هويتي إذا حاولتم معرفتها من خلال أجزاء ومقاطع.
The other thing that's also interesting that's going on here
والأمر الآخر المثير للاهتمام الذي يحصل هنا
is the fact that intelligence agencies --
حقيقة أن وكالات الاستخبارات --
and it doesn't matter who they are --
ولايهم أياً تكون --
they all operate in an industry
فجميعهم يعملون في صناعة
where their commodity is information,
حيث السلع الأساسية هي المعلومات،
or restricted access to information.
أو تقييد الحصول على المعلومات.
And the reason their information has any value
والسبب وراء أن هذه المعلومات لديها قيمة
is, well, because no one else has access to it.
أنه لا يستطيع أي أحد غيرهم الوصول إليها.
And by me cutting out the middle man
ومن خلال قطع هذه الصلة
and giving it straight to you,
وإعطاء المعلومات لكم مباشرة،
the information that the FBI has has no value,
تصبح المعلومات التي يمتلكها مكتب التحقيق الفيدرالي بلا قيمة،
so thus devaluing their currency.
وبالتالي تخفض قيمة سلعتهم
And I understand that, on an individual level,
وأتفهم أنه على المستوى الفردي،
it's purely symbolic.
يكون الأمر مجرد رمزية .
But if 300 million people in the U.S.
ولكن إن قام 300 مليون شخص في الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية
started doing this,
بالقيام بما أفعله
we would have to redesign the entire intelligence system
سيتوجب علينا إعادة تصميم نظام المخابرات بأكمله
from the ground up.
من الألف إلى الياء.
Because it just wouldn't work if everybody was sharing everything.
لأنه لن ينجح أمر نشر الجميع لكل شيء.
And we're getting to that.
ونحن نقوم بذلك الآن.
When I first started this project,
عندما بدأت بهذا المشروع،
people were looking at me and saying,
كان ينظر إلي الناس ويقولون لي،
"Why would you want to tell everybody what you're doing, where you're at?
"لماذا تريد إخبار الجميع عما تفعله وأين أنت؟
Why are you posting these photos?"
ولماذا تنشر هذه الصور؟"
This was an age before people were Tweeting everywhere
كان هذا قبل أن يقوم الناس بالــ "تويتينغ" في كل مكان
and 750 million people
و 750 مليون شخص
were posting status messages
يقومون بنشر رسائل "الحالة"
or poking people.
أو "لكز" الناس.
So in a way, I'm glad that I'm completely obsolete.
لذا بطريقة ما ، أنا سعيد لأنه عاف علي الزمن تماماً.
I'm still doing this project, but it is obsolete,
وما زلت أقوم بهذا المشروع ولكن عاف عليه الزمن،
because you're all doing it.
لأنكم تقومون به جميعاً
This is something that we all are doing on a daily basis,
وإنه أمر نقوم به جميعاً ويومياً،
whether we're aware of it or not.
بغض النظر إذا كنا على علم بذلك أم لا.
So we're creating our own archives and so on.
فنحن ننشأ أرشيفنا الخاص بنا، وهلم جرا.
And you know, some of my friends have always said,
وتعلمون ، بعض أصدقائي قالوا لي دائماً،
"Hey, you're just paranoid. Why are you doing this?
"مهلا ، أنت فقط مجنون بالشك، لماذا تفعل هذا؟
Because no one's really watching.
لأن لا أحد يراقبك حقاً.
No one's really going to bother you."
ولا يضايقك أي أحد."
So one of the things that I do
ومن إحدى الأمور التي أفعلها
is I actually look through my server logs very carefully.
هي النظر في سجلات السيرفر خاصتي بدقة شديدة.
Because it's about surveillance.
لأنها عن المراقبة
I'm watching who's watching me.
أنا أراقب من يراقبني
And I came up with these.
وحصلت على هؤلاء
So these are some of my sample logs.
وهذه هي بعض عينات من سجلاتي.
And just little bits and pieces, and you can see some of the things there.
فقط أجزاء ومقاطع ، وتستطيع رؤية بعض الأمور هناك.
And I cleaned up the list a little bit so you can see.
وقمت بترتيب القائمة قليلا حتى تتمكنوا من رؤيتها.
So you can see that the Homeland Security likes to come by --
بحيث يمكنك أن ترى أن وزارة الأمن الداخلي هنا --
Department of Homeland Security.
وزارة الأمن الداخلي.
You can see the National Security Agency likes to come by.
ويمكنكم رؤية وكالة الأمن القومي هنا.
I actually moved very close to them. I live right down the street from them now.
وانتقلت في الواقع على مسافة قريبة جداً منها. أنا أعيش في أسفل الشارع الآن.
Central Intelligence Agency.
وكالة الاستخبارات المركزية.
Executive Office of the President.
المكتب التنفيذي للرئيس.
Not really sure why they show up, but they do.
لست متأكدا حقا لماذا تظهر، ولكنهم يظهرون.
I think they kind of like to look at art.
اعتقد انهم يحبون رؤية الفن نوعاً ما.
And I'm glad that we have patrons of the arts in these fields.
وأنا سعيد بأن لدينا رعاة للفنون في هذه المجالات.
So thank you very much. I appreciate it.
مع جزيل الشكر والتقدير.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Hasan, just curious.
برونو جيوساني : حسن، مجرد فضول.
You said, "Now everything automatically goes from my iPhone,"
قلت، "الآن كل شيء ينشر تلقائيا من الآي فون خاصتي"
but actually you do take the pictures and put on information.
ولكن في الواقع أنت تأخذ الصور وتضع معلومات.
So how many hours of the day does that take?
فكم ساعة في اليوم تقضيها في عمل ذلك؟
HE: Almost none.
هو: تقريباً ولا واحدة.
It's no different
إنه لا يختلف
than sending a text.
عن إرسال رسالة نصية.
It's no different than checking an email.
ولا يختلف عن فتح بريد إلكتروني.
It's one of those things, we got by just fine before we had to do any of those.
إنه من إحدى الأمور، التي نقوم بها قبل القيام بأي من الأمور السابقة.
So it's just become another day.
فأصبح مجرد يوم آخر.
I mean, when we update a status message,
أقصد، أنه حين نقوم بتجديد رسالة "الحالة"،
we don't really think about how long that's going to take.
لا نفكر حقاً بالمدة التي يجرى اتخاذها.
So it's really just a matter of my phone clicking a couple of clicks,
فهي حقاً مجرد مسألة النقر على هاتفي بضع نقرات،
send, and then it's done.
إرسال، وتم الأمر.
And everything's automated at the other end.
وكل شيء آخر يجرى بشكل آلي..
BG: On the day you are in a place where there is no coverage, the FBI gets crazy?
بي جي: وفي اليوم الذي لا يوجد في المكان تغطية لاسلكلية، يجن مكتب التحقيق الفيدرالي؟
HE: Well it goes to the last point that I was at.
هو: نرجع بذلك لنقطة الأخيرة التي تحدثت عنها.
So it holds onto the very last point.
وتدعم نقطتي الأخيرة.
So if I'm on a 12-hour flight,
فإذا كنت على متن رحلة تستغرق 12 ساعة.
you'll see the last airport that I departed from.
سترى آخر مطار غادرت منه.
BG: Hasan, thank you very much. (HE: Thank you.)
بي جي: حسن، شكراً جزيلا. (هو: شكراً)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)